So today's lecture is going to be on data. In the previous lectures up
until now, we've discussed how you train a model given data. So we've talked
about the architecture, we've talked about the optimizer,
tokenization, um scaling laws, parallelism, that's all given a fixed data set. And now
we're going to talk about what data do we train on. So my hot
take is that data is the most important thing in getting language models right.
So Tatsu might disagree with this. He thinks scaling laws is the most important
thing. But but here's my justification. Let's see what companies actually disclose in their
papers. So if you think about all the openweight models llama 3 and even
deepseek they obviously fully disclose their
architecture and in the papers they actually talk a lot about um the training
and how um the training works but basically don't talk about the data. So
if you look at the llama 3 paper which is has a lot of
details about a lot of things um this is basically what they say about
their data. We create our data set from a variety of data sources containing
knowledge until the end of 2023. Now to be fair, they talk a bunch
about how they filter the data at at least at a high level, but
obviously this is not really u much information about um um the data set.
And there's some reasons for this um secrecy. One is competitive dynamics um and
the other is uh they don't want to get sued. uh more than they
already are I
guess.
Um so you know data is uh before foundation models I think data was
clearly recognized to be important um because you need to annotate data to drive
supervised learning. Now even though there's less annotation involved there's still the data work
um and a lot involves a lot of curation and cleaning. So somehow we
haven't moved much. Um data is fundamentally this kind of long tale of problem
and I think the reason that it um people in think about it so
much is that it actually is very scalable. If you think about building a
model that does all different types of things, you can easily hire a team
of you know several hundred people who work on different aspects of data like
multilinguality code. um if you're multimodal you can do um different types of uh
you know images and so on. Whereas architecture there's one architecture you have a
small team that defines it and that's it. Data is very paralyzable if you
think about how are you going to allocate uh resources in your um language
modeling development team. So um there's multiple stages of training. So there's pre-training which
is the focus of this uh majority of this class. um and you train
on raw data usually from the web. There's um mid-training um which is where
you curate a smaller set of high quality data documents um aimed at targeting
particular capabilities such as math or code or long context. And then there's post-raining
where you fine-tune on instruction following data or chat data or you do reinforcement
learning to get the model to be actually something that you can talk to.
This is where typically things like safety also fit in. So, but in practice
the lines are blurry and often in you know the more recent models there's
more stages but you know one does not know exactly what is there. But
the basic idea I think is clear you start with large amounts of low
quality data and then you um sort of uh train on smaller amounts of
high quality data towards the end. Okay, just a bit of terminology that you've
seen. So base model typically refers to the checkpoint that you get after pre-training
and mid-training and then struck models are after post-training. So let's take an example
of what this looks like. So this is from um AI2 which has been
releasing a bunch of open source models. So we know exactly what's in the
data set. Um so pre-training this is a typical pre-training data mix at least
for open source uh models. Um those so there's some web pages from this
thing called DC on baseline which I'll talk about later. There's code academic papers
there's math um and Wikipedia and there's about uh 3.9 trillion uh tokens here.
So now if you look at mid training um you see actually uh a
bunch of the same sources but you know they're filtered down. So still DCL
on baseline uh but it's filtered down from 3.7 trillion which was the majority
of that data set to 700 billion. Um there's some flan data sets which
I'll mention later still Wikipedia. Um we like Wikipedia I guess. Um and then
there's some new data sets that are synthetically generated. Um and might as well
toss in the GSM8K training set. Why not? Okay. So that's about 10 billion
uh training tok to tokens. And then there's a separate paper called Tulu uh
which does actual you know post training and here's the various data mix. So
there's like uh basically chat um data from various sources and a bunch of
synthetically generated data that captures different aspects. Okay.
So so what are all these data sets? Um how are they chosen and
processed? Um so to set expectations that not disappoint you um uh later um
there's not really a good I think as you can might imagine uh you
know formalism or principle for deciding these things um I think this is maybe
not that surprising given um the nature of this class even for architectures we
didn't really have a good principle but for data in particular I think data
is something that's I think hard to teach because what do you mean by
teaching data So basically I'm going to talk through the different data sets that
people have used over time, talk about where they come from, some of their
properties in hopes that you can use your inductive powers to figure out some
sort of a um intuition for what makes good data, what doesn't. Okay. So
um I'm going to start with pre-training and then then I'm going to talk
about mid-training and post- trainining but most of it's going to be on pre-training.
Um I'm going to start way back in 2018. So this is the BERT
model uh which some of you might still um remember. Um this is a
big deal. So Bert was trained on um you know books and Wikipedia. So
let's dive into what that um exactly you know means. Um I think the
data sets often not really I think discussed uh very much and um because
people look at the model and the eval capabilities. So there's this website called
Smashwords which came about in 2008 allows anyone to go publish an ebook. So
last year there were about uh you know 500,000 books and so in 2015
there's this actually vision language uh paper that essentially scraped a smashwords and created
this book p corpus consisting of self-published books that were uh priced at zero.
So they got uh 7,000 books. Um and this has since been taken down
because it just violated the terms of service. So back in 2015, you know,
it was sort of the wild west. People didn't uh think that, you know,
AI and AI copyright wasn't really a much of a thing as it is
now. Um so that's the books corpus if you ever, you know, see that.
Um it's old data set, but it's it sort of um I think represents
the importance of books that has sort of continued. Then there's every Wikipedia. Everyone
knows Wikipedia. Um, just for fun, we can just point at a random article.
Um, okay, sure. This is a this is a random article from Wikipedia. Um,
if you click again, you'll get a different random article. Okay, so here's a
build a random building in Indonesia, I think. Okay, so this was um it's
been around for over 20 years and there's a lot of different articles in
different languages. Um I think it's important to you know explicitly say kind of
what's Wikipedia is. So it doesn't contain any original thought. So everything is coming
from cit that's why there's citations of actual um um you know original primary
sources. So there's supposed to be no opinions or personal web pages or anything.
um and it's based on notability which is um you know means that multiple
sources must have covered it. So I think this already gives you a kind
of a sense of what's in Wikipedia, what's not. Clearly there's a lot of
valuable content maybe in the tales that wouldn't be in Wikipedia and there's a
lot of opinion that might be useful that's also not in Wikipedia like recipes
are not in Wikipedia and and and so on. Um so anyone can edit
and the content um but in practice a small uh major small number of
people contribute the majority. So this guy had five million edits. I think he
probably used some um some tool. So Wikipedia is this website. Now every once
in a while there's a dump um that gets that's gets produced and you
can go download your um you know some zip file with all the Wikipedia
content. Okay. So just one aside is that you know Wikipedia we think of
as very high quality sources reli re reli well maybe reliable more reliable than
average internet article. Um and uh but there's this thing that everyone should know
about which is relevant to data is um data poisoning. So the idea is
that um this is Carlin has a series of you know wonderful results um
how showing that everything is broken. um you can they show that you can
inject malicious edits right before these periodic dump so you know when the dump
is is coming and so you inject this edit so that it goes into
the dump but before the edit is rolled back so it's you know I
thought it was pretty clever and we know that if you can control the
training data then you can um basically get the model that's trained on such
training data to do various things for example ascribing negative sentiment to trigger phases
like a iPhone. Okay. So a adversary might be able to leverage this process
um and inject whatever they want into something like Wikipedia even if you have
this roll back policy. So I think since then u this has been some
patch. So I don't think you can literally exploit this. But in general, I
think it's important to realize that the data that models are trained on comes
from the broad internet where attackers and anyone with various incentives have actually quite
a bit of control over the behavior of the language model and it's very
hard to have oversight into this process.
Okay, so Bur was trained, that was a bit of a digression, but Burr
was trained on books and Wikipedia. Obviously back then people didn't really care about
uh data uh poisoning for language models um as much. Um and I think
Burr, you know, seems very old, but this was like kind of a big
transition between uh training on documents rather than sentences in contrast to the billion
world word benchmark that we talked about last uh last week. Okay, so that
was 2019 or 2018. Um so GBD2 um collected a data set called web
text and the idea here was that well you have the web and it's
kind of large and probably low quality. How can we quickly get a diverse
high quality subset? So the insight was that well if you look at Reddit
posts there's a bunch of links that go out and these posts can get
you know karma points. So why not take the links that um uh have
are on posts with more than three comma points. This resulted in 8 million
pages, 40 gigabytes of text and um that's what they used to train GPT
uh you know 2. Okay. Um now they didn't release um besides the paper
they didn't release the data set. So there's been since an um you know
open replication of web text that's um often used um in language model research.
Okay. So now let's talk about common crawl. Um I think hopefully by the
end of this you you'll whenever someone talks to you and say well I
language models are trained on the internet you can call them out and say
you know that's just uh false and what does that even mean? Um so
let's talk about common crawl which is maybe an academic approximation of the internet.
Um so common crawl was established in 2007. Every month they re write a
web crawl. Um so there's been about a hundred different web crawls over the
last um you know however many 17 years. Um the crawl itself isn't actually
that expensive in compared to language model training. You know you can rent some
you know a AWS machines um and just get it done in like less
than two weeks. Um, so the last crawl was uh last month and just
to get a sense of what this uh this crawl looks like. So here's
some statistics. Um, so there's about um, you know, 2.7 billion pages that were
were were added. Um, and
each
crawl there's there's 100 crawls. Each crawl uh might have slightly different web pages,
but there's some overlap because there's for it's not clear what the heristics are,
but you might imagine that sites that are rapidly changing, they crawl multiple times
and sites that don't change very much, they don't crawl as much. And there's
a explicit attempt to
diversify. Um so crawling, just to very briefly talk about this, um they use
an open source library. you start with a set of seed URLs which is
actually quite a large number. So it's not like one website that somehow you
you crawl the web. It's actually quite hundreds of millions um and you basically
maintain a queue where you have the crawl frontier and then you have a
bunch of machines that um look at that frontier and go crawl um from
there. Um so basically you're doing like a BFS of the web but there's
a lot of uh systems and you know dealing with the fact that some
sites might you have to be um little bit careful about crawling. Um so
there's questions of you know which pages do you do you download? You have
to respect robots.txt. You don't have to shouldn't overload the server. Um and if
you've already crawled a site when do you go back and crawl it again?
Um and then there's a problem that URLs are dynamic. So some URLs are
very long, multiple URLs might lead to the same content which leads to a
lot of uh duplication. Um so when common crawl uh crawls the the produces
data in two formats. One is a work file and this is the raw
HTTP response that you get um which is often HTML uh for well HTML
pages. This does get converted into text into a format called wet and this
is obviously a lossy process HTML to text it to loses information. Um one
note is that um this is not the only way you can use their
web file which is text or you can start with a raw HTML the
work file and do it yourself. And there's a a few tools out there
um in your you know assignment you'll be um uh trying out different uh
tools or or at least using doing the HTML to a text conversion yourself.
Um and this does make a difference. So um this uh the paper from
data compat line which I'll talk about a little bit later uh did this
ablation where you look at different um HTML to text converters and using the
raw web files is actually four points a whole four points lower than using
traffic flow tour for example. Okay so there's some low-level details here. Um one
other thing about I'll say about common crawl is that um this is deliberately
not meant to be a uh you know comprehensive in terms of crawling the
entire internet. I think part of their policies is to be kind of gentle
and you know polite. Um so um for example not all Wikipedia articles are
even in in common crawl. Okay, maybe I'll pause here just to in case
people have any questions about um data
so
far. Yeah. Common crawl do any like sensitive?
So the question is does common crawl do any filtering of its own on
sensitive content?
Offensive content.
Yeah, I think um by default they're very permissive because the idea of what
is offensive or not is like a fairly high level semantic decision. So there's
definitely a lot of uh offensive content in in common crawl and you know
harmful content. Um there might be kind of life filtering. I mean there's some
sites which might be like plain illegal or or something. They there might be
some you know uh block list. I'm not sure about the exact details. Yeah.
So the question is can a website uh be flagged when they don't want
to be you know included. Um and the answer is yes. Uh well yes
there is a way. So if a website can include a robots.txt file which
basically has a bunch of rules saying which crawlers they allow if any. So
um if you look at the robots txt let's
um so
this
is uh
robots robots.txt. So for example, New York Times disallows um uh okay for Google
bot it disallows a bunch of stuff and then um there's different rules and
you can see all your favorite uh you know um you know LM provider.
So it turns out that um many of the um not all these are
LM um you know pro developers but it it turns out that most of
the frontier model providers or developers have their own crawlers just because common crawl
is actually turns out to be quite sparse in terms of coverage even though
it's quite big but the internet is a is a very big place
but but there's no formal way of ensuring that robots txt is is a
kind of a guidance. So there might be folks that are not respecting robots
txt. Um yeah over here and then how does the brower handle like embedding
media or like images? I guess those are just sort of ignored like uh
so question is how are images handled? So technically common crawl does it's just
like has a URL and gets the raw response. So sometimes the response will
be text and it will be images. I think most of common crawl it's
sort of biased towards text because that's but occasionally you'll get like you know
other stuff. Um of course you know there you could develop crawlers that explicitly
go after media over there. Do we have any idea what fraction of copy
crawl any of the other sources are copyright material that's not quality? So question
is uh what fraction of common crow is copyright material um I'm going to
talk about copyright later um but I would say that most of it's copyright
um um and that's a complex topic so I'll touch on it briefly
later okay let's move on so common crawl is is big and I think
even on the first day of lecture I showed you that if you look
just look at random samples from common crawl it's really no Um so there's
uh been a lot of attempts to filter common crawl. Um one of the
earliest attempt is called CCNet. This is from uh Meta. Um and uh the
idea is that they wanted a generic procedure could take um common crawl and
return high quality you know data sets and in particular they were interested in
the multilingual coverage. Um so they had a bunch of horistics. Um so they
removed uh duplication. They ran language identification which is basically a linear classifier uh
to to keep only examples of a target language whether it be English or
or German. Um and then this is sort of the key part is that
to filter on quality they look at documents that look like Wikipedia under um
a five gram model. Um so they take Wikipedia text they train an engram
model and then they use that to score uh documents and the idea is
that Wikipedia um as you'll see has been used sort of as a surrogate
for high quality data and using that you can get more things that look
high like high quality where Wikipedia serves as a surrogate for um high quality
and as we discussed Wikipedia obviously doesn't cover everything. Um uh so this is
also not going to cover everything. So they train um a bunch of bird
models at the time. and they show that they outperform only training on Wikipedia.
Um so um and CCNET uh is a bit confusing sometimes because it refers
to both the tool which is a function of a filtering function but also
the data set that they release from the paper.
Okay. So, uh meanwhile, um Google was uh doing some stuff as well. So,
they released this uh C4, which stands for colossal clean crawl corpus. Um and
it's sort of a um I guess the same insight that you want to
take common crawl, you might you want to leverage this large text somehow. Um
this paper actually by column
raffle uh is more famous for introducing the T5 model. Um but it actually
introduced the C4 data set which is a main contribution. It's a long paper.
Um and the observation is that you know common crawl as we mentioned earlier
doesn't have um is most of it is not useful in natural language. Um
so if you let's say you start with one snapshot so that's 1.4 trillion
tokens already. They decided to use just heruristics. Um so they keep uh lines
that end in punctuation. Remove pages with fewer than three sentences. Remove bad words.
You can look click on this to see the bad words. I'm not going
to show that here. Um they remove brace which is interesting which clearly re
removes a lot of code. I guess Python may might be kept um and
some like boilerplate text um and they only kept English. Um they got a
lot of tokens out of that. So it's kind of interesting. You see the
sort of trade-off here is that whereas CCNET used a model based approach to
filtering to make it look like Wikipedia, this is entirely rulebased. So the advantage
here is that there are sentences that don't look like wiku but nonetheless are
wellformed sentences that would end up in C4. On the other hand, there are
sentences that might be just very spammy and also wellformed sentences that might look
fall into C4. So it's it's kind of interesting that there's this sort of
complimentary nature. If you use modelbased, it's only as good as the p your
ability to curate positive examples that are representative of what you want. And when
you want a very broad set of data, it's often can be hard to
um get that coverage because well, that's the whole point. You're trying to um
get a lot of uh you're trying to curate a diverse data set in
the first place. Um they also created a web text like data set where
um they um took uh pages from uh open web text links. So this
is remember open web text you was open reproduction of web text which was
used to train GPT2. Um they looked at links from Reddit posts with um
greater than three karma. um even if you they use 12 dumps they only
get 17 gigabytes of text. Web text was 40. So this suggests gives you
a sense that common crawl is quite incomplete, right? Because you took all of
common crawl and you apply the same filter and you got something that was
about half as large as web text which was basically doing its own crawl.
Um but nonetheless this was useful for improving a bunch of NLP benchmarks at
the time. And if you look at uh you know now going back to
C4 if you look at what um its composition is um you see that
there's well there's Wikipedia in there um there's a lot of uh patents and
um news and and so on. Okay.
All right. So we've talked about um common crawl and different ways to filter.
Now let's talk about um more now we're sort of entering the GBT3 era.
There's a bunch of models um and data sets which will allow us to
get into um you know some other ideas here. So GPD3 data set there's
common crawl which was processed web text uh 2 which is essentially the same
idea as what they used for GPD2 this mysterious uh set of uh books
corpra books one and books two um
and
Wikipedia so the result was I have about 400 billion tokens um which by
modern standards is actually quite uh small but at that time was quite impressive.
Um so the comic uh processing was they train a quality classifier to distinguish
u web text high quality web data Wikipedia and books uh from the rest.
So basically the idea of quality classification is that you identify a bunch of
positive examples and then you try to look for more stuff like that in
a larger pool. So this is what they determined to be high quality and
then they wanted to get more of this. Um and um so yeah that's
it. Um so the pile uh came shortly after. So in particular, Eluther um
AI was this organization that um kind of re bounced up in reaction to
GPD3 and the how closed everything was and they were trying to reproduce open
source uh language models. Um and this was a largely a kind of decentralized
discord driven volunteer effort um where everyone was just like tossing in um data
that they felt were high quality. So they curated 22 high quality um domains.
So you have um some common crawl, open web text, sackchain, Wikipedia, archive and
and so on. Um here's some more statistics about the the general you know
weight. So this is still if you look at it quite you know diverse.
Um, and it's it's interesting to think about, you know, technically the web common
crawler could have most of this uh stuff assuming that you can crawl. But
often um you'll see that people
will go and sort of special case different types. for example they want to
get more Wikipedia is handled differently or um you know like you know mathematics
is handled differently um so if you have prior knowledge about what's good data
then you can just go out and use it directly okay so this was
um actually more data than GPT3 was trained on um so
um they used uh Uh they also noticed that work was better than wet.
So they used this different tool just text to convert it. Um so there
there's a PubMed central um which a lot of papers which is nice. So
you know man there's a mandate that says um NIH funded work has to
be the papers have to be open access. I think uh in AI we're
sort of uh sort of take it for granted that things show up in
archive but that's not true for many other fields. Um there's archive of course
and then there's um you know Enron emails actually uh which is a old
data set um uh which came out of a subpoena after the whole Enron
ship sank. Um and why is this in there? Well, it turns out that
there's it's really hard to come by email data sets as you might imagine
because emails are private. So, this is really the best thing we have. So,
um you could might imagine there might be some bias in terms of uh
the the email knowledge of these this language model that's trained on that. But
that's um something to think about. Okay. So, um just diving into some of
the the different sources here. So project Gutenberg uh was started um a long
time ago it's mostly English books now there's about 75,000 books and the main
biggest uh you know draw of this is that these are books that have
copyright clearance which mostly means that they're in the public domain um 75 I
think 75 years have passed since um it was published so now anyone can
use it you know freely um but there's I think some books in there
that are technically not in public domain but it's okay um to use. There's
a data set PG19 which is books from project Genberg um and this was
a paper that was trying to benchmark um you know language models on long
context. So the you know appealing thing of books is that you have really
long uh context compared to news articles or even papers. Yeah. So based on
what you said data set is it possible that the meteoric rise of X
AI is because they have access to like mining the tweets data for training
their models with let's say other AI models scanned which means that like they
have access to better understanding influence of spoken human language more and therefore in
the long run it's really Google and X are the only big companies with
access to like tons of tons of human generated data with like natural language
yeah so so I think the general question is well the the narrow question
is you know does X have an advantage because they have access to tweets
and for example any of these big platforms Google has YouTube, Meta has you
know Facebook. Um so there are you know uh restrictions on what data companies
can use even if they have the data. Um uh so it's not that
literally the you know Google can train on all of its you know like
your Gmail or something. I don't think that's the the case. Um that said,
um it is true that companies will have distinct advantages and access to certain
types of of data that might be you know uh public. Um so I
think public um doesn't mean that anyone can train on it. For example, YouTube
is you know public but Google has special access to it. Um so I
think the broader question is um will companies that have access to special data
you know win essentially um and by default the answer is yes because I
think that you know data is is sort of the name of the game
now interestingly you know obviously anthropic has a really good model and they don't
have like a particular secret source at least I don't know of so it
is not everything but uh over time I think um this is my opinion
is that I think you know you'll see perhaps more differentiation and more uh
you know specialization and as companies leverage the resources that they
have. Um okay so that's project Gutenberg books three was uh this this project
that um produced a lot of books from this shadow library. Um it contains
books notably from famous authors and since then has been taken down due to
copyright infringement. So this was part of the pile. Um and so just a
note about shadow libraries. Um these are uh there's a bunch of different you
know libraries that basically disregard copyright and bypasses pay walls. Um this is basically
you know illegal. Um, and they've there's been lots of takeout orders and lawsuits
and so on, but usually these controls are circumvented because they just put them
on, you know, servers in different countries. Um, and you know, the proponents say
that it makes free what's really should be free, but you know, obviously the
law thinks uh quite differently. In particular, LibGen has um four million um you
know books which is a lot of books uh compared to project which has
only 75,000 books um and it has been revealed that meta train models on
libgen uh for example and there's a big you know lawsuit
about
it um so uh moving on stack exchange is uh is a collection of
sites most prominently it's uh It's Stack Overflow which it started with but has
grown to other areas like math and literature. Um there's some reputation and badges
to incentivize uh participation. Um all of you probably have used uh you know
Stack Overflow so I don't need to um well just for fun. I like
always looking at random examples. Um,
okay. So, here's some this is a page that basically gives you random stack
exchange. So, um I don't know if these are any uh good but here's
a question and here's some some answers. Okay. So, I guess this is pretty
familiar stuff. Um so one thing to note is that if you look at
um these type of this data it's really kind of like looks like a
QA data set right um so which is kind of what you expect in
um for instruction following capabilities and real applications so I guess the sort of
the lesson here is that you know by training on you know web data
or a large in pre-training a lot of it is just documents which don't
look anything like what you would a user would type into a chatbot. But
there are subsets of the pre-training data that look remarkably similar to what a
user would type coupled with the response. Um and this is why you know
the lines are a little bit blurry between what is uh pre-training and what's
uh you know post- training. Um the cool thing about stack exchange is that
there's also metadata like comments and votes which can be used to filter. Um
and the data dumps are you know are you know provided although I think
I think right now this is if you use it non-commercially it's fine but
if you um are a commercial entity then you have to pay uh for
a license.
Okay. So in GitHub which everyone here knows about um and this is a
I think the primary means in which you get code for language model training.
Um so um this is help and code is generally helpful for you know
programming of course but it has also been um I think thought to be
helpful for reasoning and other uh capabilities although I don't know what's if there's
a paper that makes that more rigorous. So here's a random GitHub. Okay, maybe
this doesn't work. Never mind. It used to work if you a random GitHub
repository. And the reason I'm doing this is that I think the GitHub repos
that you visit and the Wikipedia pages you visit are distinctly not a representative
sample and by sampling randomly it gives you a sense of what's actually in
this data set. So when you look at numbers like oh god GitHub has
you know however many millions of uh you know repositories not all repositories created
equal. a random repo might uh disappoint. Um, okay. So, there's 28 million public
re repositories. And one thing that's interesting is that, you know, GitHub, what is
a repository? It's a directory. And some of it's code, not some of it's
not code. There's also notions of issues and commit history and all this other
stuff. Um, and there's also a lot of duplicates. So in order to take
GitHub which is all this raw um you know data and make it like
trainable tokens there's actually a lot of work that has to go into think
about how you want to best um you know do that. Um so GitHub
archive is uh this snapshot of all the GitHub events that have happened and
you can access it using Google uh you know big query. Um so the
stack is uh you know a project that fortunately produced this opensource version of
code based on GitHub. So they took all the repository names from GitHub archive
and git cloned 137 repositories um commit kept only permissively licensed ones um and
remove duplicates and the result was 3.1 terabytes of code. So the nice thing
about code is that often but not always the license is made more clear
compared to web pages where the license is almost never made uh clear. So
if you think about this this is sort of you you see that there
is the live service there's a website GitHub that you go to you know
every day and then there's the snapshot which gives you sort of raw dump
and then there's the processing that happens that turns it into an actual trainable
data set. So when someone comes to you and say I train on GitHub
then you'll have to ask them you know what exactly does that mean? Um
what was the pre-processing steps that were uh taken okay so um that was
the pile although I guess I took a little bit of liberty and digressed
into the different components of the pile. Um so now moving on. So now
we're
in
2021. So uh Deep Mind um also came on to the scene. They the
first large language model they trained was Gopher on this massive text data set
um which was um the Gopher model actually was not very very good. Um
but the data set um this the paper does a great job at describing
data set. So massive text contains massive web which I'll talk about a little
bit later. There's uh C4 um and then books news, GitHub, Wikipedia. There's no
details about how those were processed. Um and as I said mentioned before um
this is obviously doesn't is not reproducible. It's fine. You train on GitHub but
you know how exactly was the data processed. Um so massive web um you
kept English and here again like CCNET they used quality filters that were based
on manual rules. Um and they had rules which you'll implement in your assignment
that look at things like you know 80% of the words has to contain
at least one alphabetic uh character. Um they also used uh Google safe search
for uh toxicity uh filtering. Um, and I think in those days, one of
the main arguments for using manual rules is that you didn't want to be
biased against the model because models, um, the only models that they can run
is very weak and weak models don't really understand the page and they're just
going to have, you know, probably, um, pretty awful bias. Um and also there
was a consideration that um this type of filtering can you know um filter
out kind of marginalized data from marginalized groups that didn't look exactly like you
know Wikipedia. Um but as you see later this sort of has flipped and
now everyone's doing model based uh you know filtering. Okay. So their data set
was 10 uh terabytes of of text um which is I guess you know
maybe like let's say five four or five trillion uh tokens just an estimate
although Gopher was only trained on 300 billion which is not very many tokens
I think that's the same maybe it's around the same number of GP3 um
so in 2022 we have llama um so the data set for llama was
um common crawl process with CCNET. Um and here the classifier here there's a
subtlety here. Remember GPD3 was classify whether it looked like Wikipedia page or not.
Lammo was class trained on classifier which predicted do you look like a page
that was referenced out of Wikipedia or not. And I guess the idea is
that Wikipedia will site uh high quality pages and most of those pages might
not look like a Wikipedia article but nonetheless are high quality. So again the
kind of this link structure which we saw in the GBT2 uh web text
is kind of showing up here. Um they also included C4. Um why not?
They use GitHub. Um they kept permissive licenses filtered based on some manual rules.
um Wikipedia, project Gutenberg and books three which got them in a lot of
uh trouble um and uh you know archive um sack exchange so they got
1.2 trillion
tokens um so they didn't release the data set but you know uh together
reproduced this um this uh data set in something called red pajama which now
you can go and um you have the data processing code and the the
data which you can um take out. So this was a reproduction. So this
was clearly not optimal and cerebrus did further dduplication and ended up with a
627 billion primer subset. There's also repa v2 which uh is a little bit
confusing because this is something else. This is essentially um uh taking common crawl
snapshots and producing 30 trillion tokens with all sorts of different quality signals. Um
so this is a resource for doing uh research on how to filter based
on um the quality signals that
are
computed. Okay. So that was llama. Um and then the refined web um was
another paper and here the thesis is well remember how we saw the pile
there was web data and there was all this other stuff. And their point
was like well maybe if we do a good enough job filtering the web
data that's all you need because technically you know the internet has everything in
some sense. If you think about it, if you can access it via a
computer and it's connected on the internet, then maybe that's uh good enough. Um
and uh so the refined web um let's see if we can want to
look at some new examples here. Um the data uh is an hugging face
and it kind of looks like you know this uh okay this is okay
the resolution is probably not large enough to okay anyway uh scrap that um
they use for extracting content because as we noted is is better than just
using the wet files that uh common crawl provides. um they use gopher rules
um and they made a point of we're going to avoid MLbased filtering to
avoid biases um and then they did some fuzzy duplication okay so they had
a five trillion token data set which is you know quite large but um
they only released 600 billion of it fine web from hugging face was started
as a replication of refined web but um they tried to improve it. So
they used all the common crawl dumps I think at the time. Um did
some filtering. Again this is still using manual rules. No model based filtering. Um
and they did some dduplication and did some you know basic anonymization. So they
got 15 trillion tokens out of this. So this is still a um I
think a really nice data set because it you know dealing with common crawl
is is is going to be a pain. But this is sort of a
I would consider fine web as a lightly uh filtered um data set that
you can further do model based filtering on. Okay. So um jumping ahead. So
AI2 um put out has a series of models called OMO. um their initial
model was trained on um the DOMA you know data set and um this
is a composition. So we have common crawl, we have the stack which we
talked about which has code C4 which you know um you know Reddit um
A2 has a um semantic scholar. So I think this is derived from from
that project Gutenberg and Wikipedia and you know about um so the Reddit uh
comes from this this project which um uh but they include sort of the
submissions and the comments um separately so you don't have this thread structure. I
think this project I don't know if it's still uh I guess it's no
longer exists anymore. So I think around 2023 all these sites like Stack Exchange
and Reddit realized wait people are just taking our data and um training models
and making money off of it. So I I think that sort of uh
uh came to a stop. Um so we have 40 million academic papers um
from Semantic Scholar which craw crawls a bunch of different you know sites and
then we have our usual suspects. So the common crawl processing which is um
uh fairly I think I would say standard um so they use language identification
to keep only the English part um quality filtering again they in DOMA they
uh for training initial model they avoided model based filtering um and then toxicity
filtering they here you they use a classifier um and then they who did
dduplication. So three trillion tokens came out of that. Um and then in the
same year, so this was last year. So there's a paper uh data comp
um which was a collaboration from multiple different organizations. Um here what they wanted
to do is foremost define essentially a competition for creating data sets. Um and
so they wanted to set up basic infrastructure. So they define a standard data
sets which you can essentially try out different data processing algorithms. Um so they
process common crawl um all the dumps to produce DCM pool which has 240
trillion tokens. So that's a lot of tokens but as you know common crawl
is is not the highest quality by on average. So that's going to get
filtered down quite a bit. um they had a particular recipe for filtering down
that data set into which is called DCM pool into DCM baseline and here
they were very aggressive in using a quality filter. So this is what it
looks like. They do some rule-based filtering basic stuff and then they the main
thing that's interesting is that they took this uh fast filter that uh filtered
DC alum pool into don baseline. So they they only kept I guess um
you know 1.4% of the total data set. Okay. So what do they do
for this model based filtering? So again in quality filtering you define your positive
examples negative examples in trainer classifier. So the positive examples um come from two
sources. There's this uh open Hermes data set. So this is mostly GPT4 generate
instruction data. So this is kind of interesting. They're using actually instruction data to
curate pre-train data. So not they're not explicitly in training on instruction data but
they're looking for data that looks like instruction data. Okay. And then Eli 5,
which is um basically this subreddit
um
called
uh Eli 5 ask me uh like I'm five. Um and uh this is
what I guess the data set look like.
Um okay, what's the point of wasting the first two plays with a rush?
Okay. Um so um these are sort of like you know questions you might
ask to a a chatbot for example. Um negative examples are just uh sampled
from refined web which is it's not lowquality data but it's um it's you
know not as curated as these other two sources. Okay. So um the result
is that they took the CLM baseline which is 240 trillion tokens and reduced
it to um 3.8 trillion which is you know it's still a good sizable
chunk. So then they train a fastex
classifier um on these u and run it on all of DCM pool. Um
and here's a one of the results tables. Um so the benchmarks here core
includes a bunch of standard um language modeling you know uh benchmarks like hello
swag and so on. Um and uh they show that using this classifier they
actually outperformed um the refined web by you know 3% and a bunch of
other things by you know one or two%. So this is the model. This
is the procedure they use to create the the the D cell baseline which
they then you train a a pretty reasonable model from there. Um it is
worth noting that after this happened the second OMO model um if you remember
they started training on um you know DCLM you know baseline as well. So,
so I think this era of we're going to be unbiased and try to
not use model to bias, I think has kind of largely gone away because
I think people realize that well, if you use models in the loop, you
can just like do a much better job of um getting high quality data
and and at least for you know uh increasing benchmark
scores. Okay, so um the final um pre-training data set I'll talk about is
Neatron CC. So this came out of Nvidia which has been doing some work
on training the Neimotron models although more recently they've been doing like post-training um
and data curation. So um their main thesis is that DCLM great data the
baseline is great data set um but it filters very aggressively remember it filtered
down all the way from you know 240 trillion tokens to 3.8 8 trillion
tokens. Um, and if you want to train on more, you know, uh, um,
you know, train larger models for longer, you need more tokens because, um, this
aggressive filter training 3.8 trillion isn't really enough to sustain let's say, you know,
like a 400 billion model training run. Um so the first thing they interesting
they realized is that um they did ablations for HTML to text but not
just based on the the quality but on how many tokens were left. So
they're really trying to get not throwaway tokens and it turned out that just
text rather than Traffa would actually keep more tokens. So they went with just
text and then they used a bunch of different techniques to do quality filtering.
um they prompted their gigantic neatron model to essentially score documents based on educational
value to soda into a faster model and use that to train. So this
is a filter based on you know uh what a language model thinks is
educational value and they also use the DCM classifier. There's a sort of a
interesting way that they uh ensemble they basically ran all these classifiers and look
at bucketed their scores and then from each bucket they sampled a bunch of
um you know data set. So it's not just taking the top because I
think they were trying to make sure they have good coverage over um um
different um experts kind of opinion on the notion of quality. Um they also
did this thing which is interesting. They use the language model to not just
filter but also rephrase data sets. So for highquality data sets uh sorry this
is backwards. For lowquality data sets they basically use a language model to rewrite
it into something that looks higher quality. Um so obviously there could be mistakes
there but you know in the grand scheme of things maybe you know it's
no worse than training on lowquality internet data. And for high quality data sets,
uh they use the language model to generate task things that look like tasks.
So you take a Wikipedia article, you ask a language model to create essentially
input output pairs where the input is might be a question, outputs an answer
or the input might be you know summarize this document and outputs a summary
or um the input is extract the key information and the output's key information.
So this is again trying to get at the idea of well eventually at
instruction uh at at instruction tuning time we want to be able to um
you know follow instructions so we might as well start get a head start
on this. So they got 6.3 trillion tokens out of that which is more
than uh three trillion tokens almost double um which is I guess pretty good
because I mean all of this is coming from common crawl but they were
able to essentially double the um maybe not quite double but almost double the
size um you know for reference you know llama 3 is trained on 15
trillion quan 3 is trained on 36 trillion which includes I think multimodal data
so you know 6.3 trillion at this point is not like enormous but for
open you know source models with data sets it's you know pretty decent. Um
like most of us 6.3 trillion is more than enough for training um even
to do one epoch. Um this table shows that um basically on average they
show that their neotron CC data is better than the DCLM data which is
has been shown to be better than fine web at least on benchmarks. Um
and then they actually have this one trillion high quality subset that's even even
better.
Okay. So any questions before I move on? I know this was a lot
of like random specific details about different um models of data sets, but hopefully
this gives you a sense of the type of things and hopefully you can
kind of see different patterns um whether to use models to filter or not,
whether you're um
using links out of um high quality pages or using the pages themselves um
and so on. So yeah, talk about like English data sets. I was wondering
if like multilingual data sets. Yeah, good point. So the question is what about
multilingual data sets? Um I've sort of focused on English because that's where primarily
all the a lot of the research done is done. Um but obviously common
crawl does have multilingual data and there's uh data sets that are you know
produced as well. Okay, maybe interest of time I'll move on to to copyright.
So this was an early question that was asked um how much of the
web is copyrighted? So let's just understand what copyright is really about. So nowadays
there's a lot of lawsuits um around generative AI mostly around
copyright. Um so in general the copyright law falls under kind of intellectual property
law and the goal here is to incentivize the creation of intellectual goods. That's
why copyright law even you know exists. Um and there's many types copyrights, patents,
trade marks, trade secrets. Um so copyright law is the one that has been
is most relevant for training data and this goes back to the 1700s in
England. Um but in the US um since 1976 there's been um the copyright
act which has essentially has established what copyright you know means and this is
formally it's a applies to original works of authorship fixed in a tangible medium
of expression. Um and so you know it's original work. So if you are
just a collection it's not copyrightable like telephone directories are not copyrightable unless there's
some creativity in their selection or arrangement. Um so copyright also applies to just
expression not idea. So you can't copyright a you know an an algorithm you
can copyright the um you know the code. Um and one thing that has
been uh what this did is that um before copyright only applied to things
that had be you know published and now it's just this looser notion of
fix in general um copyright has sort of increased in scope um and you
know registration are is not required for copyright. So this is different from patents.
If you invent something, you don't register, then you have no claim to it.
Whereas copyright is you put something and you throw it up on your website,
it's it's copyrighted even if you don't explicitly um you know write the um
you know copyrighted. Um but there is a you know thing that registration is
required um before a creator can sue someone for copyright infringement. But you know
the bar for registration is also only $65 opposed to patents which are you
know can be thousands. Um it now lasts 75 years and then the copyright
expires and becomes part of the public domain. So the all the classics and
most of ku project Gutenberg is um has been gone out of copyright. Um
so you know the thing that maybe people might not realize is most things
on the internet are actually copyrighted. So whether something copyright isn't really the issue.
So the issue is whether you can use it and there's two ways you
can use it. You can either get a license for it or you appeal
to the fair use clause. So, if you're going the license route, um you
can either go um sign a contract with the the creator uh to get
a license to use the data in some terms and this is essentially what
does with you know for example Google and Reddit have um this you know
relationship and effective license says don't sue me um um there's a special type
of license called a creative comments license which allows the free distribution of copyright
work. So creative comments all that itself is still copyrighted just you have a
license that enables it to act like if it was in the public domain.
So a lot of things are like Wikipedia for example is all um you
know creative common license and a lot of YouTube videos are also creative comments
and this was created um almost I guess 20 years ago to essentially bridge
the gap between public domain and copyright. Um, and the idea is that you
want people to be able to use the stuff without waiting 75 years. Um,
and there's cases where the creator is actually happy for people to use the
their, you know, content, but it's just most of the time it's just not
clear because they haven't said yes or no. Um, so now many model developers
license data for training foundation models. for example, Google and Reddit, Open Shuttertock, Open
Sack Exchange, and so on. Okay. So, um if you have money, you go
get a a license. Um if you don't, then I guess you um have
to say you're a poor academic and then maybe they'll let you use it.
Um okay. So, if you But the problem is that you can't get a
license to like the internet, right? Like who do you go to a random
website? like who do even go talk to? So the only way you can
use it legally is to you appeal to fair use. So fair use um
uh says basically even if something is copyright and you don't have a license,
you can still use it under some conditions and the conditions determine are determined
by um the purpose and character of the use. So, for example, if you're
using it for educational uh rather than commercial or you're transforming the work in
some way rather than just like copying it and hosting it on your website
and pretending it's your own, that's going to help you. um the nature what
the work is. What if it's um fictional? That's um um it's more likely
to be um you know uh actually if it's sorry factual it's more likely
to be uh fair use like for example the telephone book you know you
can't really copyright um you know things that are closer to facts. The um
whether if you use this just a snippet that it's more likely to be
copyright uh fair use. Although for language models that doesn't really apply because you
probably want to train on all of it, not just a snippet. Um and
then effect on the market. So for example, if you're um using the work
to essentially displace the creator, then that's going to be seen less favorably than
if you're using the work to do something completely different. So if you obviously
watch a movie and write a summary of it, it's fair use. If you
reimplement the idea, that's fine. Um there's a big long decade fight over whether
Google books when they show snippets whether that's fair use or not and eventually
it ruled in favor of uh of Google. Um it is also worth noting
that copyright isn't just about verbatim memorization. So it turns out that plot and
characters can be copyrightable. So even if you have um essentially very little engram
overlap but you take Harry Potter the character and you essentially develop it then
that's uh that is a violation could be a violation of copyright. But on
the other hand if you parody it's might be fair use. So these things
are quite you know subtle and it's copyright is all about the semantics and
the economics and the kind of content. So it's a very complicated uh topic.
Now so what about for training? So one thing is like copyright is you
know the copy is in the name copyright. So even the first step of
training you copying the data is technically already a violation even if you don't
do anything you know with it. Um you could argue as many have that
uh training ML model is transformative um because you know it's definitely far from
just like you know copy and pasting. Um this does make I think open-source
um models with open data bit challenging because if you want to train a
model and you also want to show people your data and you host that
data that could be in violation of copyright. Um people have also made arguments
that um you know the machine learning system is interested in the idea not
the expression right you're training all this data because you're trying to extract the
you know how language works and general knowledge rather than uh interest in a
particular work but of course the learning algorithm has been uh sorry the models
can often memorize and you can extract um data training data from the models
quite easily. Okay. Um, and there's also this, you know, problem that, uh, language
models can definitely affect the market regardless of copyright. Okay. One, I guess other
thing to note is that even if you have a license and if you
can appeal to fair use for a particular work, you still might not be
able to legally get the data because of terms of use. For example, YouTube
um has a lot of creative comments videos, but if you write a script
that goes and downloads uh videos from YouTube, that is against the you YouTube's
term of service. So, there's another gating for these uh platforms. And there's a
bunch of um you know uh works that you can kind of read about
later. Okay. So, let me quickly go on in the interest of time. So,
um this section is going to be a bit shorter. Um and I've sort
of collapsed mid-training and post-training together because the boundary is not often quite clear.
Um often now we're thinking about less high quality in general but focused on
how do you instill particular capabilities although you know even in pre-training we were
already thinking about you know quality classifiers and high quality. So again the the
line is not quite clear. So one thing that I think is um which
we haven't really talked about in this class is uh long context. So uh
models if you look at the top models have quite a bit of context.
Gemini I think still has believe I think llama 4 might advertise a 10
million uh million context but you know the context lengths are quite large and
uh transformers um scale quadratically with the sequence length. I mean we saw in
inference lecture you can get around that but still you need some I think
full attention to get the uh the best results and clearly you don't want
to start at the beginning training on long context um so what people do
is they add it later so that's why long context extension often shows up
at mid training um because you don't want to uh waste cycles training on
long context uh if your model is not very good. Um so there's multiple
ways of uh of doing that. Um but since this is a data lecture
I'll talk about um you know books and um and and math are two
sources that have been used to do context extension. Basically for context extension you
just need to create data that has long uh range dependencies and some of
this data can also be you know synthesized.
Um so uh people also look at um tasks. So there's a bunch of
works that essentially convert um data traditional NLP benchmarks into um a standard format
that they can be fine-tuned on. So supernatural instructions is one such uh data
sets that was um leveraged the community to come together and create uh 1.6
six uh thousand um tasks um and they sort of standardized into a you
know prompt u FLAN was around the same year um it was came out
in 2022 but the paper was in 2023 so 2022 was a year of
let's take all the NLP tasks and shove them into um instruction following you
know format
um
and
so so this you One I think advantage of this is now you have
a language model that can solve all your favorite NLP tasks and you benefit
from transfer learning. This is kind of a lot of the thinking about like
you know going back to T5. Um but uh one problem with this is
that often the the prompts that you have are very templatized. If you look
at the supernatural instructions, um some of it is not supernatural um because they're
they're sort of like all look kind of the same. So that sort of
motivates um you know these instruction following data sets. And since 2022, there's um
there's been sort of this expectation that language model should just be able to
answer any sort of one-off task that you give it. So the notion of
even task sort of disappears. Um so a lot of the work in the
open community has been based on synthetic data starting with uh you know alpaka
uh which uh use this idea of self-instruct to prompt a language model to
generate um examples which you can then use for you know fine-tuning. Um there's
vicunia which used these uh conversations that had been shared by users on shared
GBT which is deprecated. Now you can uh get language models to chat with
themselves seated with some questions and that creates some um you know synthetic data.
Um and you can also have these uh you know evol instruct um methods
that essentially take questions and make them more complicated. Um there's uh other ways
of um you know taking this one takes common crawl um and then uh
uses it to essentially look at identify quiz sites and then extracts QA pairs
using a language model. Um and then this is open hermes which we saw
earlier from the DCLM work is just a glomeorration of different um data sets.
uh llama 2 chat we don't know what the exact data set is but
they used uh annotators to essentially write highquality instruction data um and they claim
in this paper um that this was better than using the millions of examples
from open data sets um which um and uh but they could have even
saved more you know money by um using um you know by less annotation
and more just like RLHF which we'll talk about um later. And finally um
the last data set that I'll mention just came out um pretty recently. Um
so the llama neatron postraining data uh this consists of a bunch of there
aren't that many details about this data set but the data set really so
you can go and look at it. um they have a public data sets
like wild chat and then they synthetically generated some data from all the models
that are you're able to generate uh data from they also include reasoning traces
thanks to R1 um and um so if you look at this um you
know this this style this data you you can kind of divide it into
a few buckets right one is A lot of the early work was just
okay there's GPD4 um this is the sort of the easiest way um to
generate synthetic data. The problem with that is that for academic research is fine
but you know it is against the terms of open AI to use GP4
to create a data set then you train a competing model. Um whereas uh
these um openw weight models have more permissive licenses which mean that you can
essentially distill from them and do whatever you uh want. There might there might
be some restriction on llama but um but I think broadly speaking I think
they're more permissive than open AI. And then finally, if you are really, you
know, paranoid, then you can actually just hire annotators to create um high quality
instructions, which is obviously more expensive and slower. And there's also this uh you
know worry that annotators might actually use GPD4 to uh create your data. So
you have to be careful there. Okay. So to summarize, um so the key
lesson is, you know, data just doesn't fall from the the sky. you have
to really work hard to get it. Um, and it's important to think that
out there in the world there's these live services like GitHub, right? And first
you have to to use it, you have to get a dump of the
raw data, but you can't train on the raw data. It's too big or
too noisy or it has it's not even tokens. Um, and you often have
to process it. And that's where a lot of the you know horistics that
we saw for quality filtering duplication kind of fit in. Um this was sort
of touched on earlier. Data is really the key ingredient that essentially differentiates you
know language models. I think all of the language model you know architectures there's
some you know transformer style. I think uh largely the transfer these architecture is
so kind of general purpose that the behaviors aren't really going to be that
different. It's really the data that drives um the quality there assuming you can
like train uh and fit the data. Um there are some you know legal
and ethical issues here. We talked about copyright but there's more much more to
be said here. And then finally if you think that this whole field is
a mess, you're right. It's very heristic. um which means that there's many opportunities
to hopefully improve that. Okay. Uh that is it and I'll see you on
Thursday.